In this lesson we'll learn a little bit about the historical context of JavaScript and also take a look at
the things we can create using JavaScript as a language. Before we start learning how to use JavaScript,
it's important to take a look at what it is and the kinds of things we can create using JavaScript.
So, one of the most
confusing things about JavaScript when people are talking about it or learning about it is it sounds
very similar to another language called Java. And it actually has nothing to do with Java as a language,
although it pulled some inspiration from the structure of the language.
They actually have nothing to do with each other. It was named JavaScript more as a marketing ploy due to
the popularity of Java as a language at the time JavaScript was created, so we kind of get that confusion in
that the names are so similar because of that. JavaScript was created in 1995 by Netscape as a language that
was native to the browser, so using it for a language to create products and applications that run directly
in the browser to replace other languages that had been appropriated to do the same thing, but didn't run as
well because they needed plugins, and things of that nature, such as Java was used prior to JavaScript in the
browser to create what is called Java applets or little bits of applications that ran in the browser,
but they were slower and it also need a plugin to be able to run that language since that wasn't what it was
designed for originally. So JavaScript was created to kind of replace that and be that language that was
meant specifically to be used on the web. And JavaScript is primarily client side, meaning it doesn't need
to run through a server in order for it to work. Compare that to something like PHP or .NET that needed to
run through a server in order for those to be able to work with a website, JavaScript just needs a browser in order to run.
While it was originally designed as scripting language, it's actually a fully featured language.
If you don't know what a scripting language is, it's basically when a language is used to communicate with an
existing application. An example of this would be using JavaScript as a scripting language in a game engine
like Unity 3D versus using it as a fully featured language to develop something like an application from
the ground up. So what are some things
we can actually create with JavaScript? Well, we can create something as simple as interactions or small
enhancements like infinite scrolling. If you don't know what infinite scrolling is, if you've ever used
something like Pinterest where you scroll down and it dynamically loads content depending on how far you are
down the page, it's continually loading content when you reach the bottom, that's infinite scrolling.
Beyond infinite scrolling and little small enhancements like that, we can create things like parallax
effects in the browser, we can create entire games that run in the browser without a plugin, we can do 2D,
we can do 3D games, and also JavaScript is starting to be used more and more outside of the browser,
which is really interesting. This term has been coined for that called the Internet of Things, and that refers
to languages like JavaScript being used in contexts other than what they were originally designed for,
things like communicating with robots, creating wearable technology, and things like that, so it's really,
really cool. We can do a whole lot of different things using JavaScript.
It's also been used to create entire applications from the ground up.
An example of this is a YouTube application for PlayStation, it was built with a JavaScript library called AngularJS.
So let's take a look at some specific examples of things that were created with JavaScript.
So this is another JavaScript library called parallax.js, which allows you to create parallax effects.
I'll just X out this little menu over here so we can take a look at this.
You can see that as I'm moving we get that kind of parallax effect and I'm using my mouse almost as the camera to kind
of manipulate and change the viewport. So, to see what JavaScript's actual role in this web page is,
let's take a look at the code that's running this behind the scenes.
So I'm going to right-click and pull up the developer tools here by pressing Inspect Element.
I'm using Firefox, so we're using Firefox's developer tools, and I'm going to start by disabling JavaScript.
So right here we see the default behavior of our page, and then if I come here into the Settings I can come
down here and disable JavaScript and we're going to see a change, so I'm going to click that.
And, now you can see we don't have JavaScript working so you can see that kind of inner activity that was adding here
to our page. We still have some basic animations and movement coming in, but this is actually being done
with CSS. If we come in here and disable our CSS, I'm just going to press these little eyes, which is going
to turn that off, we can see just the HTML on our page. We can see we have images, we have basic content here,
but we have no styles and just a very basic inner activity such as the ability to click on links.
So this is what HTML does is it gives the structure to our page.
When we come in here and add CSS back in, we have the presentational aspects of that page being styled with CSS.
So this kind of sets the look and feel and we can start to do more and more as CSS advances, such as basic animations.
When we come back in and bring JavaScript back in, we can do a whole lot of different things, very cool things
such as interacting with our web page. So here you can kind of see the separation of those three languages,
or technologies, and see how they each have their own role within the web page.
So let's take a look at a couple other examples that were
created with JavaScript. We have this demo here, Samsung Racer,
which is an example of 3D in the browser. This was created using a library called Three.js, which allows you to
create 3D like this here directly in the browser without using a plugin or anything like that, which is really,
really cool.
Another example that was also built with Three.js is this little guy right here, this is more of a CAD type
example where someone has created a mockup of an apartment, but we can use our mouse to kind of look around
and control the camera, and in addition to that we can actually use our keys here and move around and take a look as well.
So you can see a more practical application of 3D in the browser.
You can send this to your client and they could actually walk around your mockup and get a much better feel
for what you're creating or what you're designing for them, which is also very, very cool.
Another example is with a motion controller. This is called Leap Motion, which is a motion controller that's
controlled using your hands. You can see he's using his hand in this demo here to manipulate or control the
scene, kind of move the camera, and in just a second here he is going to start to use his hands to actually
interact further with this and pull off pieces of the skull. You can use JavaScript to create all of these
kinds of interactions. So, there are a lot of different things even beyond the browser that we are able to
do with JavaScript. So, now that we've learned a little bit about the historical context of JavaScript and what it
does and also taken a look at some examples of what we can create using JavaScript, in our next lesson we're
going to actually get started
and write some JavaScript of our own.