In this lesson we will learn how to have more control over our conditions by using comparison operators.
In our last lesson we ended in an exercise
to calculate to see whether a number is divisible by 3 or 5 and alert a different word under each condition.
Otherwise, it would just print our number out to our console, but one issue with our code so far is if our number
is 0, which is not divisible by 3 or 5, it's still going to alert fizz or buzz.
So just to kind of test this out I'm going to comment out our randomNumber here and this brings up another
good point. We can comment out a single line of code, so it's not run, by using two forward slashes.
So we can press two forward slashes and then you can see our code is turning gray and that it's no longer running.
So I want to say var randomNumber and set it equal to 0 so we can test our code under this condition and see
what's going to happen. So if we run this you can see we get fizz.
So from this we can see we're not having exactly the right thing happening.
So I'm going to go ahead comment out our 0 and bring back in our randomNumber variable.
So how can we fix our code so 0 isn't going to alert fizz or buzz?
Well we can use what's called comparison operators to check for additional conditions in our code.
So we want to check for an additional condition. Let's start with our first condition if it's divisible by 3,
and we say if it's divisible by 3 and another condition has been met.
And the way that we can do that in JavaScript is by using two ampersands.
So we can say if randomNumber is divisible by 3 and this other condition.
So what we want to check for here is that our number is not equal to 0.
So we haven't learned how to do this yet. So we have an operator, a special operator, that checks whether something
is not equal to something else. So we want to target our variable, so we want to say randomNumber is not equal to,
and the way we do that is with an exclamation point and an equal.
So we want to say it's not equal to 0. So this is kind of confusing at first, but we really have to start to
retrain our brain how we're thinking and to read things how it's going to evaluate in our code.
So just to go over this once again, we're going to say if our randomNumber is divisible by 3 and our randomNumber
is not 0, then we're going to alert fizz. So we want to do the same thing for our second condition.
So we also want to say, and if our randomNumber is not equal to 0, then we can alert buzz.
So only if both of these conditions are met then will we do this.
So let's go ahead and test this with 0 again to see if we fixed this issue.
So, let's run this and you can see now we're just getting 0 echoed out to our console, it's no longer alerting
fizz or buzz, so awesome. We've fulfilled that condition that if our randomNumber is 0 it's not going to return
any of these answers. So I'm going to comment this back out again and we have an additional condition now that
we want to meet. We are kind of building in the complexity of our program here.
So we're going to say if a number is divisible by 3 and 5 alert fizzbuzz.
So we're going to add an additional condition here. So right under this we're going to say, else if,
and then our additional condition. So we want to check and see if our randomNumber is divisible by 3 and it's
also divisible by 5. So we want to see if our randomNumber is also divisible by 5.
And then we're going to alert something different, we're going to say fizzbuzz, so fizzbuzz.
Then we just need our semicolon, but in our current program we're never going to get fizzbuzz because our range is
only between 0 and 5. So now we're going to choose a random number between 0 and 15, that way we have a possibility
of this condition being met. So we're going to multiply this by 15 instead of 5.
So, let's go ahead and run this. So we get fizz, we get buzz, fizz, and we can continue to run this or we can
just set our randomNumber to 15 to see if we're going to get fizzbuzz and our code is going to work.
So I'm going to comment this back out and then we'll set our randomNumber to equal 15 and we should get fizzbuzz.
So let's go ahead and run this. And we can see we get fizz. And so we're getting the exact same problem
where we were getting 0 in that we first need to make sure that condition isn't met in our first if statement
here because otherwise we're never going to get our last statement.
So clearly we need to evaluate this a little bit differently in our code.
So, right below here, well let's go ahead and keep what we have so far, but start thinking about how we can
improve this so we don't get that result. So, we're going to start again with our randomNumber and see if it's
divisible by 3, so if it's divisible by 3, and it's not 0. So if it's not equal to 0 then we're going to have
some conditions. So just from the start we want to also check if it's divisible by 3 and if it's also divisible
by 5 so we can get fizzbuzz. So what we can do here is we can add an additional if statement inside of another
if statement. So let's take a look at what this looks like. We can say if our randomNumber is also divisible
by 5, then we'll alert our fizzbuzz, otherwise, we're going to alert just fizz.
So otherwise else just alert fizz because it's not divisible by both.
So this is going to be kind of confusing at first, but we can really start to slowly build up the complexity
of our code by testing it under a certain condition and really making sure it's doing exactly what we want it to.
So we have our first condition, so let's go ahead and add our second condition.
So we want to say, else if our randomNumber is divisible by 5, and then we still want to check if it's not 0,
so and our randomNumber is not equal to 0 we want to alert buzz, otherwise, we want to just log our number to
the console. So we can say console.log and then our random number.
So now let's go ahead and test this. We're going to go ahead and delete our original code and evaluate it and
see if 15 will now return fizzbuzz instead of fizz. So let's go ahead and run this, and you can see we get fizzbuzz.
So, this is awesome. You can see that even though it took us awhile to get to this kind of end result and to
get to something that works just by slowly coming in here and testing this under certain conditions,
we can make sure that we are getting the results we intend and we're not accidentally letting things kind of
slide through like we were before. So we have to be creative and build on the complexity using the smaller
parts that we know. I know this isn't a very exciting example, this isn't very fun to do something,
an exercise like fizzbuzz, but it really can help us retrain our brain to think in a way that we can
translate our thoughts into code. So, now that we've learned about control flow and how we can use and,
and not equals, and also use if/else statements inside of another if statement to improve what we're checking for,
in our next lesson we're going to be putting it all together and doing something a little bit more fun
by creating a zombie text adventure game.