In this lesson we'll put everything we've learned so far together to create a simple zombie text adventure game
Up until this point, we've learned
a lot of things so far and we've definitely learned enough to do something fun like create a little text
adventure game to help us practice thinking in a new way, because just like I mentioned before, we really are
training our brain to think in a new way. So I want to create a little text adventure game called Zombie
Apocalypse where we chose a weapon to fight the zombie with and we have a 50/50 chance of either defeating
the zombie or getting bitten and losing the game. So, just like we did with our fizzbuzz game we can start
to break this down into parts to make it easier to write our code.
It's really easy to try to do everything at once and then get really overwhelmed.
So, the first thing we want to do with our game is we want to kind of set the scenario or set the scene.
So, I'm going to use alert to alert on the page what kind of scenario we're encountering here.
So I'm going to say alert, and then we're going to enter a string into our alert, and just to save you the
time of watching me type this out I kind have written a little example scenario.
So you can feel free to create your own or you can type in what I've created here.
So I'm going to say, oops and it cut off my it, It is the zombie apocalypse.
You are looting a store and suddenly a zombie bursts through the door, which I'm going to go ahead and shrink
this window a little bit so we can see more of our Scratchpad here.
So we have our zombie apocalypse, we're looting a store. So let's go ahead and run our code so far.
So we get a little message and we've done a good job so far of kind of setting the tone.
So we can say OK. And next we want to ask our user to choose a weapon.
So we want to store our weapon choice as a variable so our code can remember what our choice was and we can
refer to it throughout our code. So we can say, var weapon, and then we want to store the results of our response.
So we can use our prompt and then we can insert a little bit more here.
We could just ask what our weapon was, but we want to kind of build on our scenario.
So I wrote something else out here. So, I'm going to copy it and then paste it so you don't have to watch me
type all of this. You could say, You search around frantically for a weapon.
What do you choose? And we have a couple of different choices here, we can choose a bow and arrow, an axe,
or a rubber chicken. So we want to add our semicolon. And let's go ahead and run this so we can see what
we have so far. So we have our beginning scenario. We have a zombie bursting through the door and we have to
search around frantically for a weapon. So we can make our choice, maybe we want to choose rubber chicken,
and then OK. So now we need to do something with our weapon choice.
So I would like to start by maybe inserting or telling the user what they chose.
So, then we can say, alert You attack the zombie with your, and then we want to add a space here by adding
a string with just a space in it, and then we can just use our variable to repeat whatever our user typed in.
So we're going to say You attacked the zombie with your weapon.
So let's go ahead and test this. We say it's a zombie apocalypse, and let's say axe this time.
So we can say, You attacked the zombie with your axe. So we already have a really good start.
We have our scenario, we're asking the user to choose a weapon, and then we're alerting our response.
So now what we want to do is we want to have a 50/50 chance of either defeating the zombie or getting bitten.
So I'm going to press Enter. And I like to keep my variables all in the same spot, that's a good practice.
So what we want to do is we want to create a randomNumber once again, so we have our fun math functions coming
back in. So let's say var randomNumber, and then we want to have a 50/50 chance so if we use our randomNumber
here and we use the rounding to round that randomNumber, then we're either going to get a 0 or a 1.
So we have a 50/50 chance of getting either 0 or a 1. So we want to say, Math.round, so we're going to round
the result of our randomNumber. So round our randomNumber. And then we don't want to multiply this by
anything cause either 0 or 1 is fine. So, now we're going to have our scenario.
We're going to be asked for our choice. It's going to attack our zombie with our choice.
And we also have this randomNumber, but we're not doing anything with it.
So this is a perfect opportunity to use our if else statement.
So we want to check and see if our randomNumber is equal to 0, and then we could have one thing happen or we
could say, else if our random number is equal to 1 then we want something else to happen instead.
And we can leave off that else statement and our code is going to run just fine, we just won't have something
if we happen to get a 2 or a 3 nothing would happen instead. So we can do something a little bit different
here with our else if statement. So if our number is 0 I want us to get bitten and lose.
So if our number is 0, we're going to alert The zombie bites you. You lose!!!.
And then our semicolon. Otherwise, if we get a 1 we can say, alert, then we can say You kill the zombie with
your, and then we can just reuse our weapon again. So we can say plus and then our space, woops,
make sure you use a plus and not our equals sign, and then with our weapon, and then we could say,
You win!, and then our semicolon. And let's go ahead and test our little game.
So I'm going to go ahead and run this. We get our scenario. And we have, oh no, a zombie bursting through the door.
We can choose our weapon, so let's say rubber chicken. So we attack the zombie with our rubber chicken and then
we kill the zombie and we win. So we can go ahead and play again and let's see if we can get bitten.
And we win again, but you can see here that we can start to do some really fun things.
We aren't just limited to doing kind of boring exercises like fizzbuzz.
By slowly breaking this down we can start to build things and increase our complexity.
So in our next lesson I want to go over your volume 1 assignment and learn how we can use everything we've
learned so far to create an adventure game of your own.