In this lesson, we'll learn how to write our first JavaScript.
Before we get started by writing our first JavaScript, we need a good web browser because we're going to be
writing our JavaScript directly in the browser. And we're going to be using Mozilla Firefox so if you don't
have that installed you'll want to go ahead and download that and install it.
Now, the next thing we want to do is we want to open a file in the browser so we have something to run our
JavaScript on, and that needs to be an HTML file. So in our project files, you can see we have just our 03_begin
folder and we want to open this index.html file in our Firefox web browser.
So I'm going to go ahead and double-click on this and it's going to pull open our JavaScript page here.
And you can see we just have a pretty bare bones document. We have a heading here, this is an h1 heading,
and then some basic CSS, which just changes our background color and the color of our text, and also our font
as well, so just a very bare bone project page here and we're going to be writing JavaScript on top of this.
What we're going to be using to write JavaScript is the developer tools of Firefox.
So we can right-click, come down here to Inspect Element, and it's going to pull up Firefox's developer tools.
If you have a light background and you want to change it, you can see mine's dark, the only difference I have
here is that I'm using a different theme. So if we come over here on the right side and click on this gear icon,
then you can come here to our DevTools theme and switch from the light theme, which is what you see by
default, to the dark theme if you want it to look like mine. The last thing we need to do in here is come
down here and scroll to where it says Available Toolbox Buttons and make sure our Scratchpad button is turned
on because this is going to allow us to create a sketchpad or scratchpad that allows us to write little
JavaScript files here and apply them directly to our page without having to use an external program.
We can write JavaScript directly in its native environment, which is the browser.
So I'm going to go ahead and click on this little Scratchpad button, it's going to open up our little JavaScript
Scratchpad so we can write it directly here and then we can see it in the browser on the left.
So I'm going to close our developer tools because we have our Scratchpad open, and now we're ready to go.
Before we start writing this, I also want to save our file so we don't lose any of our progress on accident.
So I'm going to come up here and save our Scratchpad as a JavaScript file.
So we're in our 03_begin folder and I already created two folders here.
We want to always make sure we're organizing our files, so our CSS is in the styles folder, all our styles
sheets in a styles folder, and so all of our JavaScript is going to be in a scripts folder.
So I'm going to double-click on this and then we can name it whatever we want as long as it follows that file
naming convention for the web. We can't have spaces or crazy characters, we're basically limited to hyphens
and underscores, or CAML case to separate any words. We're just going to call this main.js and I'm going to
hit Enter to save. Now, one thing we want to note before getting started with JavaScript is that the code you
write at first is going to be terrible, and this is completely fine, and I mean that in the best way possible,
and that's only because we can't write good code until we know what that means to actually write good code.
So the most important thing is that you get practice and learn after writing things why there might be a better
way and eventually get to the point where you can write awesome code, we just never start out that way.
So what we're doing here with JavaScript is we're going to be telling the client, or the browser, what we want it
to do using a language that it understands. So all we need to do to talk to our browser here is learn that
language, which is JavaScript. So, let's start by entering a command here, which is going to communicate with
our browser. So I'm going to type alert, which is going to alert the browser of something.
And then directly after our alert we need some parentheses, so it's going to open and close those
parentheses for us. And inside of this we need to add quotation marks so we can add some text in here,
otherwise it's going to interpret this as a command rather than some contents.
So we add those quotation marks, this is what's called a string.
So you can see our syntax kind of is being hinted here where we're telling it alert, we're going to give it a
message, and the format that message is going to be in is a string, which you can see right here.
So we're going to type in our message. And we're going to tell it Hello World, which is kind of
that stereotypical first message that we always write when we're learning a new language, so we can go ahead and
follow that stereotype. I almost feel like it's a rule when you're starting a new language and we can go
ahead and do that as well. So alert, Hello World in our quotation marks, and then we need to finish this by
adding a semicolon. So I'm going to add that semicolon and that's going to tell the browser that this is a
statement or a complete command. That's called a statement in JavaScript.
The last thing we need to do is run our code so it's going to run this JavaScript in our HTML file over here on the left.
So I'm going to come up here and run this, and very, very cool we have this pop-up window right here telling us
the message we alerted, Hello World. So we can press OK. And how cool is it that we can already have some
kind of functionality or interactivity on our page? But luckily we aren't limited to just alert, we have other
commands we can tell the browser as well. So right below this I'm going to use another command here called confirm,
so that's just confirm. And then in parentheses we have the same syntax here for this command, we're going
to enter another string or another little bit of text in between here.
So I'm going to type in those quotation marks and confirm that say, I love JavaScript, if I can type here,
with an exclamation point. And the last thing we need is that semicolon and then we can press Run.
So we have our alert saying, Hello World, we can say OK. We have this confirm, which is almost identical
to our alert except for we have the ability to press Cancel as well.
So I'm going to press OK and then there we go. So from there you can see that our program is running from
top to bottom, it's just going to start, and then read our statements or our commands as we type them in our file here.
If we come in here and add a new one, I'm going to press Enter, and we can use another one called prompt,
which is pretty similar to these two except for it gives us the ability to type in some text.
So, I'm going to add those quotation marks to enter our string here or our text, and let's say Do you want to
learn JavaScript, and then I'm going to add our question mark.
We need to add our semicolon there at the end. Very, very important we don't forget that semicolon.
And after I press Run, we're going to see our alert. I'll press OK.
We have our confirm, which is next say, I love JavaScript, OK. And then we have our prompt asking us,
Do you want to learn JavaScript? So we can press Cancel and run away or we can press OK and continue.
So I'll say Yes with a whole bunch of exclamation points because we're super excited.
And then there we go we have our first program. One question you might have is the spacing we have between our commands.
So, the space between each of these statements is going to be ignored.
So if we wanted this all to be on one line without any space, if we run this we're going to get the exact same
thing here. You can see that nothing at all is different other than it's formatted a little bit differently
in our file. So the main important thing here is that it's readable for you, it's scannable.
So it's best to start each new statement on a new line like this.
You can even press Enter to add a space between each of these.
It's going to run exactly the same. The important thing is if you add a space between this, if you have many
lines of code, you want to not leave that space between each line because it actually adds to that file size,
which we don't want, we don't want our code to run more slowly, which in a program that's only a couple of
lines long like this one it doesn't have that big of an impact, but once we start to have larger file sizes
that's going to have a huge impact, but other than that it's up to you.
It's going to ignore that space between those commands. So now that we know how to setup our JavaScript Scratchpad
and we've also learned a couple of commands for our browser, in our next lesson we're going to learn about
operators and how we can use JavaScript with logic.