In this lesson we'll learn about operators or how to use JavaScript to do calculations.
Before we get started in the browser we need to open up our project file for this lesson.
So in our project files
you'll just want to make sure in your 04_begin folder that you double-click to open up index.html and
Firefox web browser. From there,
we just want to pull up our JavaScript Scratchpad so we can write this and see it directly in the browser window.
So once again you'll right-click and click Inspect Element to pull up your developer tools and then click on this
little spiral notebook icon to pull open our Scratchpad. If you think back to our last lesson, we learned how
to use commands to start to communicate with the browser window.
We typed things like alert and then we just needed to put some text or some characters inside of quotation marks,
which is once again called a string, in order to display the results in the browser.
So we can say Hello, we just need to add our semicolon, and then once we run this you can see we see that
result popping up in a pop-up window and it says Hello, and we can press OK.
But we aren't just limited to commands like this. One of the most important parts of using JavaScript to create
programs is learning how to use operators to perform calculations for us, so this allows us to use JavaScript with logic.
One of the most common types of logic is math, so that's always a good starting point.
Even though it's not very exciting, we can get a lot more practice and kind of learn more, get a better feel
for JavaScript, by performing those kinds of calculations. So I'm going to go ahead and delete our alert here.
And one of the most common types of math or arithmetic is addition.
So if we say just how we would think of it, 2 + 2, all we need to do is just add a semicolon at the end and
JavaScript is going to evaluate this expression for us, or it's going to perform this calculation and return a result.
But if we press Run like we did with our alert, you can see we have nothing happening and this is
because we're not telling it to do anything, rather we're kind of performing a calculation here or we're writing
a statement, we're just saying 2 + 2. So, it's not going to have any kind of effect over here, but it is in
fact returning a result kind of behind the scene. So in order to see that rather than pressing Run,
we want to click up here and say Display. And what this does, you can read right here, it's going to insert
the results in a comment so we can see what kind of value JavaScript is returning behind the scene.
So I'm going to go ahead and press Display and you can see it's going to say the equivalent of this statement
here is going to be 4, so 2 + 2 is equal to 4. And in addition to addition, we also can perform subtraction.
So if we want to say 2 - 2, we can just add our semicolon, and then we can press Display, and we can see that
2 - 2 is equal to 0. If we were stuck with simple calculations like this it might be pretty tough to see how
helpful this is since we can just do this in our head, but once we start to get really hard calculations,
that's when we can start to use JavaScript to do this heavy lifting for us so we don't have to think nearly as hard.
So if we had kind of two crazy numbers here and we wanted to add these together, we could just type this in,
and then it will return the results here for us. So, in addition to this, in addition to addition,
we have subtraction, we can perform complex calculations, we can also do things like multiplication and
division as well. So the syntax for this or the symbol we use you might already be familiar with because it's
not completely unique to JavaScript. JavaScript uses a kind of common syntax for this.
So if we wanted to say, what is 2 times 2 we can use an asterisk, so 2 * 2, display the results, and we can see 4.
So if you think back or you might already can be able to guess what we can do to divide one value by another.
So if we want to say what is 2 divided by 2 we use a forward slash just like that.
So if I press Display we get the result 2/2 is equal to 1. And these are pretty simple arithmetic operators,
but we also have kind of funny ones as well such as this thing called a modulo.
So just to show you that would be 10 and we could use the % sign and then 3.
So, what does this mean? It's pretty difficult, there's not really a way you can guess what this means,
but what this is doing is it's taking the first number, dividing it by the second, and returning the remainder of
those two numbers. So if I press Display, we get 1. So how the heck did we get 1?
Well, if we take 3 we can see how many times 3 will go into 10 as a whole number.
So 3 x 3 returns 9, we can't fit 3 in another time so the whole number that's left over is 1.
So 3 x 3 is 9 plus 1 equals 10, so that returns the remainder.
And in fact this modulo is incredibly helpful in JavaScript as we'll see later on in this course.
It can start to do some really interesting things for us even though at its face value it's kind of odd seeming.
It doesn't seem like it might be super helpful. Another thing we need to kind of remember or think back to
when we're using operators like this is the order of operations.
If you took math in high school or earlier on this might come back to you or this might sound familiar,
and the order of operations helps us determine when we have multiple operators like this, which calculation is
going to be performed first. So if we have something like 30 - 2 * 3, if you take a second and kind of think
about this and think about what result it might return. So I'm just going to take a second here and then I'll
press Display and you can see 24. So if we perform this from left to right, just like we're used to,
we would get 30 - 2, which equals 28 * 3, which it's clearly not 24.
So if you don't remember what the order of operations is, it has an order of precedence in which these are going
to be calculated, and multiplication and division are always going to be performed first.
So we get 2 * 3, which is 6, and then it's going to subtract the result of that 6 from 30, so 30 - 6 is equal to 24.
If we want to have this first part performed first, we can just use parentheses to tell JavaScript what we
want to happen first, which is just like in traditional arithmetic or traditional math.
So if we put in parentheses (30 - 2) and then add our * 3 outside here, we should get 28 * 3.
So if we press Display, you can see that's exactly what we get, which is 84.
So we need to kind of be understanding of this and be able to anticipate the results, because if we weren't
familiar with order of operations you can see we would expect this to return a completely different result than it did.
And while math doesn't seem incredibly helpful on its own, we're just getting values here, but what can this
actually do for us? It starts to be incredibly important and helpful once we combine this with other kinds of
things we can do with JavaScript. And we aren't just stuck with returning the values here, it can also be
incredibly helpful to return these values somewhere else as well.
So, that's what we're going to talk about in our last lesson when we talk about the console
and what that is.