In this lesson we'll learn about the web console and how we can use it to view important information about JavaScript.
For this lesson you'll just want to make sure you open our
index.html file from the 05_begin folder and then open up our Scratchpad from the web development tools just
like we have in our last couple of lessons. And if you remember from our last lesson I mentioned that there's
a different way to display the result of the code we're running other than clicking Display and viewing it as a comment.
So just as a refresher, if you remember in our last lesson we learned how to run or use JavaScript to
calculate the results of an expression or a mathematical expression for us, and if we say like 2 + 2 and add
our semicolon we could press Display and get the results in a comment, so 2 + 2 returns 4, but there's actually
a much more common way to view the results of a statement or an expression like we see here, so I want to
take a look at that. And the way we can do that is we're going to be logging information to something called the console.
So what we can do here is we can say console, which is going to target that console, and we'll say .log,
so we're telling the console to log some information, and then we need to add that information inside some parentheses.
So just like with our alert, our prompt, our confirm, we are giving a command and then putting it inside some
parentheses and then we'll finish with our semicolon. The main difference here is now we're telling
something specific what command we want it to do. So we're saying console log some information.
So inside of these parentheses we'll say something like we did before, we can say Hello World, some exclamation
points, and then the last thing we want to do is click Run. And you can see nothing is happening is here,
and that's at least nothing visual is happening, but we need to look at a certain place to view the
information we're logging, and that's in the console, the thing we're telling to display this little message.
So the way we get there is in our developer tools. So we can right-click and choose to Inspect Element,
and then in our web developer tools, I'm going to shrink this window so we can see all of our tabs here a
little bit better, you can see that there is a tab that's called Console.
So this is where we need to go to view that information. So I'm going to click on this, you can see if we
hover over it we get a tooltip telling us we're going to view our web console, and there you go.
You can see our message here. It's echoing out the content we put inside of that command, Hello World!!
And we also get some additional important information here that when we return a result like this or we have
information that's logged into our console it's going to tell us what line that occurred on, so if we have
tons of code we can go and see exactly where we're seeing the results of that command or that code.
So right here you can see we are viewing on line 14, so it's the last bit of information after that colon.
And if you look over here in our Scratchpad you can see we entered that command on line 14 as well.
When we have code that's this simple it's not that helpful because we remember where we entered it, but if we're
getting an error or a warning or something like that, it's going to display in our console as well and that will
be incredibly important especially when we have hundreds of lines of code or code we haven't written in a long
time and we're coming back to it to do what is called debugging or solving issues or errors in our code,
then that's going to be really, really, really helpful. So, just like I mentioned before we can see other kinds of
information here. You can see we have information from the network, from CSS, JavaScript, security, etc.,
so there's all kinds of additional important information here as well that's unrelated to JavaScript.
So this is going to be one of our best friends when we're writing software or programs for the web,
it's going to know where to look for information. So let's take a look at what a warning might look like.
So over here we can put out a warning, and while this isn't a real warning it will kind of emulate one so we
can get a good idea of what that might look like when we see one in our code.
So we can use a similar command here. We're going to target the console and then we're going to say,
console.warn, so we're going to echo out a warning here, and then just like before in our parentheses we'll put
our warning. So we can say, Warning!!!, and then add our semicolon and then as we run this you can see that
we have now a warning being echoed out. Normally it would be something more specific about what kind of warning
we're getting, right now it's just putting whatever we entered into here.
And you can see that it's different from information that's just logged to the console with console.log.
We have a little triangle with an exclamation point here saying that this is a warning, you need to watch out for
whatever it is that we're doing, and then you can see what line the warning occurred on.
And more serious than a warning is an actual error, something that is going to cause a serious issue in
our code, so we can kind of take a look at that as well. And that's just console.error, and then in quotation
marks we can say Error!!!, add our semicolon and run this, and we can see what an error might look like as well.
You can see that it's in red so our eye is going to be immediately drawn to this, it looks kind of scary,
and we have an X as well. In addition to that if we drop this down we're going to get some additional
information about the nature of our error and then once again the line it occurred on.
And don't worry about what these errors are saying right now, it's a little anonymous, it will make more sense
as you learn more about JavaScript more as you go along. The most important thing right now is to recognize
the difference between these and what they look like. So, how is this helpful you might be asking yourself,
if we're giving our own warnings, we're creating our own errors right now?
And one of the most important parts of this is that we can interact with our code as it's already running on our page.
So we can get different messages, different information about our code as our page is live rather than writing it,
and then running it, and then seeing the error. So, we can type in things just like we do in our Scratchpad in
the console. So if we wanted to say console.log, we can put in the exact same thing, Hello World!, and then
we can just press Enter to run that code and you can see we have what we typed in, Hello World, we have a
little message that says undefined, which we'll learn what that means later, and then we have the
actual information logged to our console. The main difference between adding this in our console and in our
Scratchpad is that our code is already running here on our page as we're typing it in here, and we're also
limited to typing it line by line, unlike in our Scratchpad where we can write an entire file or as many
lines of code as we need to get what we want to do done. So, it's an important difference there as well.
If we need just a little line or two here and we don't need to save it we can put it in here, otherwise,
we need to add it in a file or write it in our Scratchpad. So, this is one of the most important concepts to
understanding it and get a grasp of because as you get more advanced, as you get more familiar, it's going to be
an essential tool to help you find errors in your code. So console.log, chances are you're going to be using this
a ton throughout your JavaScript career. So now that we've taken a look at the console and learned about what
it can help us do, in our next lesson we're going to continue on learning more about JavaScript and talk about
different types of data that JavaScript recognizes.