In this lesson we'll learn about primitive data types or the basic building blocks of JavaScript.
Up until this point we've used
two different types of data with our JavaScript or two types of things.
So let's take a look at what we've learned so far. When we learned in our last lesson that we can log things
to the console, we use the console.log command and we put a value inside of these parentheses or something we
want to echo out in the console. And you can see right here it's expecting us to input a string.
So a string, as I mentioned before, is a string of characters or a sequence of characters inside of quotation marks.
And we can type anything in here we want, it doesn't matter, it's all going to be treated like a string.
So, we also learned how to use JavaScript to calculate math for us.
So we could say 2 + 2, we can display the result, and we can see that it's 4.
So, why is it important to understand that this is a string and these right here are numbers, that might be obvious,
yes these are two very different things, but what's most important about understanding this is that JavaScript
treats different types of data differently. So to take a look at this we can see 2 + 2 is equal to 4,
but what if we add 2 different things that are not numbers? So, let's say 2 +, and then I put the 2 in parentheses,
we now know that this is a string, anything inside those quotation marks is going to be treated like a string.
So what is the results of this expression or this statement, what answer are we going to get?
Well, let's go ahead and take a look, I'm going to press Display.
And you can see we get 22 returned as our result and not 4, so huh?
That's kind of weird, and what's happening here is when we have 2 different value types here, when we have 2
different types of information we can add them together, but our result is actually 22, and what this is called
is concatenation. So this is where it's incredibly important to understand the difference between two
different data types because JavaScript treats them differently.
So here when we have two numbers it's going to add them together.
When we have two different data types, when we have a number and a string, it's going to concatenate them or
just kind of push them together into a result, which is also a string.
So, what it's actually putting out is like this, it's just saying 22 is the result of that.
And for example, if we add two different words or strings together, let's say we have Hello + World,
so we have one string we're adding to another string, take a second and kind of guess what the answer of this might be.
So if we press Display, you can see we're getting a string returned as a result as well and it's just concatenating
those strings, or it's pushing them together. If you notice here it doesn't add a space between our two words
here because JavaScript doesn't know that those are words, they're supposed to be separate.
It can't read our mind so we have to kind of anticipate these types of results as well.
So if we want to have a space in there we have to say, Hello, and then add or concatenate a space,
so inside of this string we need just a space, and then we can add again and we can say World.
And now when we display the results we get all of this concatenated so it'll push it together,
this Hello, plus, the space, plus the World, and then the result is something more like what we expect to see,
or more like we recognize as we can see below, but really it's just a concatenation of all of these things.
So, this can be incredibly important if we accidently have a number that is being treated as a string,
if it's being converted somewhere in our code we might get something like 22 instead of 4, which you can see
is much, much different so we have to be understanding of how these are treated and be able to watch out for
that kind of result when we have something kind of strange going on that might be what's happening.
So, we have other types of values or data types as well. So we have numbers, we have strings, and we also have
other things that can be outputted, other kinds of values. So, let's take a look at that.
Let's say we have 10 is greater than 2. So let's go ahead and display the results of 10 is greater than 2.
We know that this isn't going to return an answer like obviously 2 + 2 is going to return 4, so what happens here?
I'm going to press Display and you can see that we get true as an answer, so it's saying yes, 10 is greater than 2.
So if we say that 10 is less than 2, if you take a second and try to guess the result, you can see that just
like we expect it's going to tell us no that's false, 10 is not less than 2.
So, this is different. We have true and false, different type of data than a string or a number.
So what kind of data is this? Well, we can actually ask JavaScript, which is really cool.
We could use the typeof command. So we could say, typeof, and then we can add in parentheses what we want to
know the type of. So we can say 10 is less than 2, give me the answer of that, what type of value is being returned?
And now when we display this we can see it's returning boolean.
So, true and false are called Boolean data types. You can see I've created a list here to kind of serve as a
reference and kind of help reinforce this because this is a lot to take in at once and I realize that.
So it's really important to take your time in understanding this.
This will start to make more sense as we go along so don't stress out if you don't understand all of this right away.
It's more important to be aware of this concept that there are different data types in JavaScript because we
are going to use these as the basic building blocks of our program.
We have Boolean values, these are incredibly useful, we can check to see whether something's true or false
and then write our code based on the response. And usually this won't be such a simple example like it is
with numbers. So I'm going to go ahead and delete these. We have a couple of other data types as well.
And these data types are kind of strange. You can see right here we have two others called Null and Undefined.
So, we'll get a better idea of what these are as we go along, but just real quickly, Null means a value does not exist.
So if we ask JavaScript something that doesn't have a value, it's going to say that value is Null,
and if we ask JavaScript something that hasn't been defined to it, if it doesn't understand it, it's going to
return Undefined. So I know those concepts are kind of confusing at first, but it'll start to make more sense,
especially in a couple of lessons when we start to use something called variables in JavaScript.
So to get some more practice about data types, let's play a game here.
This is in game.html and we'll just work through the first one together and then you can do the rest on your own
between lessons or come back later because this is incredibly important to be able to anticipate what type
each expression's result is going to return. So if we say 300 / 2, we can see it returns a value, which is 150.
So if we take a guess at what type this result is, it's a number.
And to try and check our answer we can say, typeof 300/2, and then just display the result.
We can check to see if we were correct as it will tell us what that answer is.
So, kind of take some time and practice between learning these types here in our little game and then join me
back in my next lesson and we'll go over the answers here and we'll also talk about something incredibly
important, which will help us start to actually do things with our
code when we learn about variables.