In this lesson we'll learn how to use variables to store information.
In our last lesson we ended in an exercise
to start to be able to try to guess or anticipate the type of an expression's result.
So I want to go over some of these answers and take a look at that.
We learned that the result of 300/2 was 150, and 150 is a number.
While that seems kind of obvious to us, it's not as obvious to our code.
It doesn't really understand what a number is that's actually defined for it in a certain way in the language
itself and JavaScript itself, so we have to be able to understand how JavaScript is thinking about each of
these things. So let's take a look at Hello + World. And if we press Display here we get the result.
We can see it's crammed together, but it's kind of hard to understand in the context of our Scratchpad what
the results will be here. So I want to take a look at our console so we can get a better idea.
So I'm going to bring up our developer tools and come over to our Console tab and then just enter exactly what
we entered in here. So we can see Hello + World, and we're going to ask it what the result is and it's going
to tell us that that's Helloworld. And now it's much easier to see that this is a string, that our result
is a string, so we see those little quotation marks and we don't see them over here.
And if you remember when we added two numbers together it returned a number, but if we add two things that are
not numbers together it concatenates them and returns it as a string.
So this is what we're seeing here. And JavaScript doesn't know that these are separate words, even though
these are readable to us, we have to remind ourselves constantly that we aren't reading this like text on a page
or something like that, it doesn't understand these are words. So it's just going to cram it together,
it's not going to know that there's a space in there. So if we wanted something like that we'd have to say
Hello and then add in that space ourselves, and then add in our World, and then we would get the result.
It would just read this as a string too and insert it. And although this looks very readable to us it's
actually just pushing it all together and we're actually getting three separate strings here concatenated.
So we have to constantly remind ourselves to think in a new way when we're writing that code.
So we have Hello World, it's returning a string. So how about 4 is less than 2?
So we type in 4 is less than 2 and you can see we get false, and if we remember back to our last lesson
false is a Boolean value, we have true and false, which are both Booleans.
So if we ask it what typeof 4 is less than 2 is, it's going to evaluate 4 is less than 2, it's going to
return false as we see here, and then it's going to ask what type of the result is.
What is the type of false? And then we get boolean return, so very, very interesting.
And continuing along we have a+b, which I want to do that last and there's a reason why, which we'll get to in
just a second, but 3 + 6, if we add this together, so 3 + 6, we have a number here and we have,
this looks like a number to us, but since we put it in quotation marks it's actually being treated as a string
so JavaScript treats it as a string. It doesn't know that that's a number since we didn't treat it that way.
And then we get it concatenated and returned as 36. So if we say, typeof 3+6, then we can see it returns a string.
So we have to remind ourselves also that it's going to concatenate those numbers and it's going to
return it as a string. So, how about a+b? If we say a + b, it's going to return an error and say a is not defined.
So this is actually a special type, if we say, typeof, let's say c this time, it's going to say that its type is undefined.
So this is another value type as well, which we started to learn about in our last lesson.
So how do we correct this error? What if we want to use c and have that mean something in our code?
We have to create what is called a variable, which is going to define things for JavaScript.
So it's no longer going to be undefined, it's going to have a definition in our code, and it's going to be
very helpful for other reasons as well. So let's go ahead and take a look at that.
I'm going to switch over here to our project file for this lesson, which is our index.html file in our
07_begin folder. And let's take a look, I'm going to pull up our console again so we can see any results
that are being spit out to our console here. And if you see this reflow, when I remove this it's just
telling us that our code is being recalculated, our CSS, we get that little reflow message.
So I'll clear that. I just wanted to point that out in case you were wondering what that is.
Let's say we want to define for JavaScript so we no longer get undefined, we need to use the variable keyword,
which is var for short. So we just say var, oops and make sure you don't have your caps lock turned on like
I did, so we say var, and then we need to give our variable a name.
So if we want to name it something like a, we can name it a, and then we need to set an equal sign so we're
telling it what it is. We're saying var, we have our variable, we're going to call it a, and then we're going
to define it using the equals sign. So let's say we want a to equal 2, for example.
Then now if we run our code and we ask what type of a is, maybe take a second and guess.
What do you think it's going to return? What is it going to tell us?
Well if we press Enter you can see it's returning a number. So since we said a is 2, now it's reading when it
sees a it's going to point to this value, it's going to say well, a is 2 and 2 is a number, so it's going to
return a number. So now we don't any longer get that undefined.
If we say var b, and we want this to be something else, then now we can use these variables anywhere we want to
refer to that value. So if we run this. So we define our variables, we're saying these exists, and now we can
say a + b, maybe we want to say a + b, if I can type that in, it's going to return 6, which is 2 + 4.
So, now we no longer get that error. We can say typeof a + b and we get a number as well.
So now we're saying it exists. It's no longer undefined. So that's why we got that error, it's saying it expected
a variable, but since we hadn't defined it for JavaScript it was telling us it doesn't know what we mean;
therefore, it's undefined, so very, very interesting. And we aren't just limited to numbers here, we can store
all kinds of information in the form of a variable. So, let's say we want to store something like a string,
we can do that as well. So we just need to use our variable keyword and we can give it a name.
So let's say we want to say my name, I could say my and then Name, which I'm using CAML case here because we can't
use spaces in variables names. It's going to treat these as two separate things so we can't have a space in
our name, and we want to set it equal to the value we want our variable to mean or what we want that definition
to be, and say I just want to put my name in here, I'm going to say Susan and then I can run my code,
which will run our code. And then I can say myName or I can type it in my console, and now it's going to return
Susan when we say myName, so that's really, really cool. If we wanted to use this with a command like we did
before we can say alert myName, and then if we run this, you got it, you can see it's going to say not myName,
but Susan because now we've defined it to mean our name, so it's really, really cool and this is a very,
very powerful essential building block of JavaScript in addition to understanding types as well.
So just to take a look at this,
a little review. We have a variable, this is a syntax, which we just saw.
So let's say we wanted to create a variable called catNoise and we want it to mean a string of meow.
Well, we have our special keyword, var, that indicates we're creating a variable.
It triggers or tells JavaScript that anything after this it's going to expect a name.
So we give it a name and then we set our name to whatever we want our value to be.
It can be a string, it can be a number, it can be a Boolean value, and we can even make it more complicated and
set it to an expression. So if we want our catNoise to equal 2 + 4 or something like that, which doesn't really
make sense, but we can set it to many things, this is very, very flexible.
But we do have some naming rules for our variables. We can't start with a number, we can't have spaces like
we saw before, which is why I was using CAML case for the name or meaning, the second word in that name I
just capitalized to show that separation between those multiple words, and we can't use reserve words or keywords.
So, examples of those are break, case, catch, continue debugger, there's a whole list you can see.
We have var, since that means a variable we can't use that. We can't use typeof since that already is defined,
it already means something different in JavaScript and you can confuse it, so we have to watch out and not use
any of these things that already mean other things as well. Beyond that, we want no punctuation except for
an underscore or a dollar sign, and as a last kind of unspoken rule we want our name to mean something,
we want it to stand for something to us. So for example, myName means something to us, it's human readable,
it's concise, and if we came back a couple of months after writing our code we would still remember what that means.
And if someone else was reusing our code or adding to it,
chances are they would understand what it means as well. So, that's just a brief introduction to our variable.
So, in our next lesson I want to continue using variables and see what other kinds of things
we can use them to accomplish in our code.