In this lesson we'll learn more about using variables in our code.
In our last lesson we learned how we can create variables,
which is almost like telling our code to remember certain things.
So let's get some more practice using those. Let's say we want to create a variable that stores our favorite movie.
Well, we remember we can use the var keyword to create our variable.
Then we just need to give it a name like myFavoriteMovie, and then we need to give it a value using the equal sign.
So, let's say we want our favorite movie to be troll 2, we can just add that, and then our semicolon.
And now we can use this variable anywhere we want in our code and do just about anything we want with this,
which is really, really cool. Let's say we just want to alert our variable.
We can say alert myFavoriteMovie, and then it's just going to look for our variable in our code, look for where
we declared it or where we defined it, and then it's just going to pull whatever value we insert in here.
So if we run this, we can see it alerts Troll 2. If we want to do something different with this, let's say we want to log
it to our console, we can use this as many times as we want in our code.
So we can say console.log myFavoriteMovie, and now we get it alerting our favorite movie and then we can get it
logging to the console as well. So this is really, really cool.
But what if we want to make this a little bit more interesting?
We can do more than just alert a variable, we can start to build on this in different ways.
Let's say we want it to alert a full response, well we can just use some of our handy operators to do this.
So I want to add a string to this. Let's say My favorite movie is, then we just need our space,
and then we're using concatenation, so when we run this we get the response, My favorite movie is Troll 2,
whatever our variable is. So this is really, really cool. Well, what if we want our variable to respond to a situation?
Well, we aren't just limited to setting our variable to a static value like a string or a number or
Boolean or something like that, we can actually use it to store the response to something that happened.
So I'm going to delete our string here, and let's say we want it to ask us what our favorite movie is.
Well we can just use a prompt, insert our question here, so what is your favorite movie?
And then if we run this, now it's going to look in our variable, it's going to use our prompt, ask us what our
favorite movie is, and we can say something like maybe our favorite movie is Gladiator, and press OK.
And then it's going to alert us whatever we inserted into our prompt.
It's going to store that information or that value that we type in our text box here and then it'll use that
anywhere we want to in our code, which is really, really, really cool.
So, let's take a look at a different kind of variable. Maybe we want a variable that stores a random number.
Well we can just use var, and then we want to give it a name, so let's say, var randomNumber, and then we can set
it equals to. And what if we want our code to generate a random number for us?
Well, there's a special command for that that already does that for us in our code so we don't have to figure
out how to write that from scratch, and that's Math.random, which is going to create a random for us.
So we use a capital M for Math, then we use .random, and then we need some parentheses.
And it's going to look at this and say okay I need to generate a random number here.
So if we were to alert our randomNumber, let's take a look at this.
I'm going to add our semicolon. If we run this now we get our prompt.
So we say our favorite movie. It's alerting our favorite movie, and now we're generating a random number as well,
which is kind of an important note here, this randomNumber command here is going to generate a random decimal
between 0 and 1. So if we wanted a random number between 1 and 5 for example, then we can just multiply the result by 5.
So you can see we can build on our variables in different ways to make them more flexible.
So if we run this, we get this asking our favorite movie, and then now we have a different number and it's 2.3,
so we can see now it's going to be not just between 0 and 1, we can get a bigger range here.
So I'm going to go ahead and delete this first part so we don't see that every time.
If we run this again, you can see now we're getting 3.8, we're getting 0.6.
And so this is really intriguing as well. So, now behind the scenes it's creating a random number for us and
then it's going to tell us that random number so we don't have to do anything here at all, it's just going to
do all of the hard work for us. So you can see that our variables can be very flexible, we can do very
interesting things, and we can have our code kind of do that hard work for us.
But what if we wanted to do things based on what kind of response we get or based on a scenario?
Well let's take a look at how we can do that in our next lesson when we talk about control flow and how to use
if/else statements to run our code under certain conditions.