In this lesson we'll be introduced to control flow or how to make our code run only under certain conditions.
Up until this point all of our code has run just from
top to bottom and it would always run no matter what, but if this was the case we'd be pretty limited in what
we could do. Fortunately there's a way we can make our code only run if certain conditions are met.
So, we can use what's called an if/else statement to run our code if a certain condition is first met.
So let's take a look at this. Let's say we want to ask a question and print out a response that tells the user
if they're right or wrong. So we can first create a variable to store our answer.
So let's say we have a variable. We declare it with our variable keyword once again, var.
We need to give it a name so let's just call it answer since we're going to be saving an answer, gathering a response.
And then we'll store a prompt. So we'll store the response to our question.
So let's say our prompt command, and then we need to ask our question in the form of a string.
So let's say we ask what the capital of New York City is or New York and we want to gauge and see if they are right.
If they answer it correctly we'll give them one response, if not we'll give them another response.
So let's say What is the capital of New York? And then the if/else statement we first need to say if,
and then we add some parentheses, opening and closing parentheses, and we need to put our condition inside of those parentheses.
So if this condition is met we'll do something else. So if our answer, and then we need to ask if it's equal to the
correct answer. So up until this point we have been using a single equal sign and in JavaScript this has a special
meaning in that it assigns a value to a variable or it sets something equal to something else instead of asking
if something is equal to something else, which is a traditional use of an equal sign that we're used to using
as we do math and things like that. So we have to ask if something is equal to something else in a different way.
And the way we do that is with three equal signs. So instead of one, we just use three.
So we're going to be asking if our answer is equal to, and then we'll put in our capital.
So we have Albany, which is the capital of New York. And then to run the code only if this condition is met
we need some curly brackets here. So we open them right after our condition and then we close them right here.
And then we're going to put everything inside of here that we want to happen if our answer is equal to Albany.
So we want to say if it is correct we want to alert the user that they're correct.
So we want to alert You are correct, and then to run our statement here we need our semicolon.
And then we need to provide an alternative in case our condition is not met.
So we have if the answer is Albany we'll tell them they're correct, and we can use the else keyword,
so we'll say else do something different. So we have if and then our condition and then whatever we want to
happen inside of our first set of curly brackets, then we have our else, and if you find it easier to read
this we can also just press Enter to bring this onto a new line, else do something different.
So we can say otherwise, let's say Sorry, and then maybe we want it to show them the response
again, sorry + we need our space, and then our answer, another space, and then the rest of our message,
Sorry that is not correct. And then we need our semicolon. So let's take a look.
I know this syntax is different than what we've been using so far, but let's take a look and see what this does.
So we're going to run this. It's going to ask us what the capital of New York is.
So we can say, maybe we guess, and we're like oh, New York City.
And we press OK. And it says, Sorry, New York City is not correct.
So, how cool is this? We now have our code responding to a scenario.
We've built a little quiz here and now we have customized response depending on what answer we type in.
I think this is just so cool. So let's go ahead and run this again.
We have what is the capital of New York? And let's say we get our answer right this time, we say it's Albany.
And then we have our response saying, You are correct. And maybe we want to add an exclamation point in here so
it's a little bit more excited about the fact that we got it right.
So we can press OK. So you can see here that we can have multiple things happening.
We can start to have a customized response or code that only runs if something else happens first.
So we're no longer just running things from top to bottom no matter what happens.
Now we can only execute certain code if something else happens first.
So this is where our code starts to be incredibly powerful and things start to get really fun.
So, in our next lesson I want to continue using if/else statements and learn how to check and see if
multiple conditions have been met.