In this lesson we will learn how to use if/else statements to check for multiple conditions.
In our last lesson we learned how to use
if/else statements to do something called control flow or to have code run only in certain situations.
So let's continue practicing using our if/else statements and build onto our quiz we have here.
So, so far we have a question, it asks us what the capital of New York is, and we get a different response depending
if different conditions have been met. So if our answer is Albany we are told that it's correct; otherwise,
we're told our answer is not correct. But what if we want to check for multiple scenarios?
Well we can see use and if/else statement, but we have to modify the syntax to be just a little bit different.
So let's add another answer to our quiz. So let's ask if, maybe what our favorite animal is, something that
has more than one possible correct answer. So let's say var favoriteAnimal, and then we want to ask a
question with our prompt command and let's say, What is your favorite animal?
And then we need our semicolon. And then we can start our if/else statement.
So our first condition we want to ask if and then put our condition in parentheses, so let's say if our
favoriteAnimal is equal to, and remember we use triple equals to check to see if something is equal to
something else, so let's say if our favoriteAnimal is equal to cat, we can alert a message like maybe Cats
are awesome!, add our semicolon. And what if we want to check for a second condition or a second favorite
animal and print out a response based on that condition and if that condition has been met?
Well, rather than using else and rather than adding another if, we can use a combination of the two so it
will check if this is met, and then we need to use something called else/if to check for another condition.
So we can press Enter to come onto a new line or we can continue on that line as well, whatever is easiest
for you to read. So we could say, else if, which is two words, we can add our additional condition,
so we could say else if favoriteAnimal is equal to maybe something like dog, or not dig, but dog if I can
type correctly, and then we need our curly brackets to check for our second condition.
So maybe we want to alert Dogs are okay. We could add our semicolon.
So we have our first condition, we have our second condition, and then we can either continue checking for
multiple conditions using else/if or we can just do our else statement.
So we'll say, else, and then we need curly brackets, we don't have parentheses here because we're not checking
for a condition we're just saying otherwise do this. So maybe otherwise alert good choice.
And then add our semicolon. Maybe we want to capitalize our sentence here so it's correctly formatted.
And now let's go ahead and run this and see what happens here.
So we have our first question. We can insert our answer. And then it'll ask us our favorite animal.
And maybe we want to say dog. And then it will check for multiple conditions.
It'll check for this one, then go to our else/if condition, and then otherwise we'll get our else.
So this is really, really cool. We can check for multiple things and we aren't just limited to one or the other.
So this gives us even more flexibility with our syntax or our formatting here for our control flow.
So, I'm going to go ahead and delete this and let's take a look and I want to try a common coding question
that's asked in interviews and it's designed to filter out candidates.
So if we can do this then it means we're doing a good job. So we're not going to use the exact question that's
asked in interviews, we're going to use a modified version, and it's a little game called FizzBuzz.
So, I have the console pulled up here and I'm going to clear it so we have all of our information cleared out and
we're starting fresh. And if you don't remember how to get to the console we just want to right-click,
bring you our developer tools, and then my screen is small so we can't read it, but we want this Console tab,
which we get that little reflow message every time we resize the window so that's what that means once again.
So we're going to press Clear. And the way we do an exercise like this is rather than trying to do everything
at once we can make it much easier by trying to start with the smallest part, and once we can do that successfully
then we can continue to build on it. It's much simpler, it makes it much easier on ourselves to think about
things one thing at a time. So let's start by trying to generate a random number.
Our goal here is we want to generate a random number between 0 and 5, if our result is divisible by 3 we're
going to alert one thing, if it's divisible by 5 we'll alert something else.
Otherwise, we'll just print the number to the console using console.log.
So, we're going to start by creating our random number. So we want to store our random number in a variable
so our code can remember that random number. So we want to say, var randomNumber.
And if you remember a couple of lessons back we used some math commands to generate a random number.
So that was with a capital M, then Math.random, and then parentheses because we're going to tell it to generate
that random number and insert the result. We'll add our semicolon.
And let's go ahead and also log what we're doing here to the console so we can see how we need to adapt this to
fit our problem here. So we're going to console.log that random number to see what's being generated,
so random number, add our semicolon. I'm going to go ahead and run this.
And you can see we're getting a number, a random number. We get a new random number every time we run our code,
but it's a decimal. And if your remember back from our math questions earlier we also learned that Math.random
generates a random decimal between 0 and 1. So, we don't want a decimal we want a random number between 0 and 5.
And we're going to be checking for whole numbers so it doesn't make sense to have decimals either.
So we want to start by rounding this number to a whole number, and it turns out there's another command for that.
We can use Math.round to round our numbers. So instead of Math.random let's test that out, it's just Math.round
with a capital M for that Math. And it's going to round whatever we put in parentheses.
So just to test this out let's test this out with a decimal that we choose.
So we say round .5, and if we run this, you can see it's rounding up so we get 1.
If we had something different here, maybe we have .3, if we run this you can see it's going to round down to 0.
So this is going to round this to a whole number so now we're getting a whole number, but we still need it to be
a random whole number. So rather than rounding whatever value we insert in there we can still use that random
number command to generate a random number. So inside of our parentheses instead of that static value we're
going to say, Math.random, and then we need the parentheses for that one as well.
So I'm going to add some space here so we can read this a little bit better.
So what we're doing here is we're generating a random number, which we saw generated a decimal.
So it's going to execute or run the code inside first, it's going to say generate that random number,
and then we're going to round whatever that random number is. So let's take a look at this.
You can see we're getting 0 and we're getting 0 a lot of times.
You can see this scary looking red number here. It just means we're getting the same results multiple times.
So, we're getting 0 five times and we got a 1. So let's take a look, we get 1 again, 1 again, and then 0.
So now we're consistently getting whole numbers between 0 and 1, or they're either a 0 or 1.
But our problem here says we want a random number between 1 and 5, so how can we change our variable so that we're
getting a range of numbers. So maybe take a second and try to think about how we might accomplish that with
our current code. Well, one thing we can do is we can take our original results here, our decimal,
and multiply it by 5. So it's going to take a decimal, it's going to multiply it by 5, and then it's going
to round that number. And this is going to have the effect of increasing our range from 0-1 to being 0-5.
So, if we multiply this by 5, let's go ahead and test this out.
So I'm going to run this and now we can already see we're getting 2, which is not in our original result so
we're definitely getting closer. And you can see we get 5, 4, 1, 5, and we can continue to test this and we
can see now we've met our first condition and we have a variable that's creating a random number between 0 and 5.
So, excellent work. So let's go ahead and continue on and see if we can do the rest of our challenge.
So, we want to see if the result is divisible by 3, and then if that condition has been met, we want to alert Fizz.
So we can use our if/else statement here. So we want to say if our randomNumber is divisible by 3,
then we'll do this. So let's come back to our condition here in a just a second and add what we want to happen.
So we want to alert fizz if it's divisible by 3. Okay, so we can come back to our condition.
So, we want our random number if it's only divisible by 3, we want it to alert fizz.
So, we can use that funny little thing we learned back a couple of lessons called modulo, which if you remember
was a percent sign. And what this does is it checks to see if there's a remainder after dividing a value by
whatever number we chose. So, we want to see if it's divisible by 3.
So using modulo it's going to check and see if our number is divisible by 3, but it's not quite right,
it's going to return a remainder, not just see if it's divisible by 3.
So what we want to do here is we want to use our triple equal sign to see if the remainder is equal to 0,
because if we divide a number by 3 and we get 0 as that remainder it means it's exactly divisible by 3 and
there's no whole number left over, which I know can be kind of confusing to think about at first, but if we kind
of break it down like this and really try to think about what's happening here we can see that this is going
to give us that intended result. So now if we have a number that's divisible by 3 we'll get fizz.
And then we want to check for an additional condition. So remember we can use else/if.
So I can say, else if a randomNumber, and just like with our 3 when we want to use our modulo to see if we
divide it by 5, if the remainder is equal to 0 then we want to alert buzz.
So we can say, alert buzz, and then we need our semicolon. So, let's go ahead and check this so far.
So, we get 5, so it's alerting buzz, 5 is divisible by 5. So we could say OK.
When we check it again we just get 4, 2, 2, and then now we're getting buzz.
So, we can say we have that working and we've met most of the condition.
We otherwise want to print the number to the console. So rather than logging it here we can just use our else
statement to only log the number if it's not divisible by 3 or 5.
So we want to say, else, I'm going to hit Ctrl+X to cut this, and then we'll log it to the console.
So, we have most of our questions, conditions being met, but if it is 0, if our number is going to be 0 here,
it's going to print the result and say it's divisible by 3 and it's also going to say it's divisible by 5.
So, technically 0 isn't divisible by 3 or 5. So in our next lesson we're going to continue learning about
else/if statements, control flow, and we're also going to use comparison operators to check things like
or and and/not.